Okay, we're going to call the order of the Miami City Council meeting for today's date and time item two
This public input and unscheduled personal parenthesis and you want to be honest with you address the council on any of the agenda
So then item three is consent agenda staff is recommending items four through six for the consent agenda
If there are no questions on any of those items, they're trying to motion to approve the percentage of the as recommended
Second roll call please
I don't have a presentation by orders in associates for the fiscal year 2017 2018
All of it in the financial statements and entertainment orders report, and he had you
I just was telling him on the way in it seemed like he was just here a couple of months ago
But he said he's never presented in this room before so it's been a little while
2018 financial statements you all shared down the big packet financial payments in your back
I'm not going to be into detail unless you all want me to
But you know
Just a couple of things first off are on the thing you was in here. It's the standard unbounded by the
The nice thing you're gentle phone
The other thing I'm sure you all were having a performer done by the conference and so I wrote some of this too
But then I'm going to be to I really
But your general fund the judge is one thing that's usually
You all know if you're right if you're an annual general fund that is a dry up and go
I wouldn't have about a month's worth of reserves and
So typically we say one to three months is a get spot to be in so you all know the low end of a good spot
Now also
I'll be ready they fund that's not part of that
You know that's another point
So I think we're a very good position
That other thing I'll be using it through the utilities
There's not a whole lot of municipalities that do the electric there are some it's not a lot
We also audit them. They do they have electric a bigger community that very similar in the activities and so I can pair of you on to
And just your revenues in your your operating income
So if you take all the new revenues and utilities and then just all of your operating expenses
You know salaries the purchase of the electric the appreciation
You know maintenance all those costs and what's up for sons of your revenues
End of about 22% you all are about 22% as well once we account for some of the years
We'll kind of one time cost
So, very consistent, there are a couple other communities called Cassini Stiller.
Also, I have a lecture there, a little bit higher.
We don't work with Stiller, so I'm not sure what would happen there.
I'll just see that if that had a couple of one-time events to the good
that is making a percent of the higher.
So, really, you're very well consistent with what we're seeing elsewhere.
So, that would encourage you.
Then the last thing, your pensions, you all have three of them.
There's the police fire and then the city police.
Police and fire, you have no control over it all.
The state runs those in the night telling you to contribute next to 70% of the police.
That's what we can do.
But, that police plan is, without a risk of being 100% of the funding.
And I think actually this year, we risked your over 100%.
So, it's a real good shape.
Fire is about 66% of the funding.
And so, you know, each city of the state is absorbing some of that liability
that remain 35% in one of the edits.
So, including mine.
But again, there's nothing you can do with that.
You can't pay extra.
You can't pay less.
You have to pay less for the state sales.
So, just to be clear on that.
So, it's 66%.
But that's a statewide pool.
Right.
And so, you're saying the state pool is two-thirds funded.
One-third, not are underfunded.
Right.
And so, the accounting state is essentially, you know, I think everyone's important at each other.
And it's who's going to pick up the tax for that third.
You know, the state's funded at the cities.
The cities are funded at the state.
And it's up on the accounting standards came in and said,
And essentially, cities you want to be picking it up.
And so, do we have to report that as a liability?
Yes.
You're, you're reporting a piece of that third.
Right.
So, along with the other, you have to have to be able to see you.
Some kind of, some proactive share.
Okay.
So, that's what the very last one is, the city's own plan,
which you all are a complete control.
You know, the state doesn't have anything to do with that.
And that plan, this is, this is, that has a journey of 17.
It's a year behind, just to get the city time to get the sense of staying in the actual
to do their thing and then for us to audit it.
You know, there's a year to wait.
So, that journey of 17, you know, we're about 70% of the time.
And so, typically, you know, what I hear is 80% of the above is considered, you know,
fairly well funded plan.
So, you all are, you know, on the downside of where we like to see you.
Now, along the flip side, you all have an actuary that also comes in and helps you all determine what the fund each year.
You all satisfied money each year.
But you're not going to pay the clients for another 20 or 30 years.
So, I must do on either the set of side now that I have these clients pulling you a 30 years from now,
but I don't know.
So, an actuary helps you.
And an actuary tells you all, here's what I think her dash remains you should pay.
you all are paying that actually to determine that.
So that's a positive.
And a lot of times that's how you get unfunded
is because you don't pay what you actually recommends
because you can't afford it.
And you're putting it off, you're putting it off.
But in your case, you are funding what you actually are deciding.
And do you remember, say, 15 and 16?
Well, are we trending upward or?
I've been over the last four or five years.
It's been about 65 to 70% somewhere in that area.
And out of the last four years, I think two years,
you actually paid more.
You've funded more than what the actuary is said.
The other two years, you've funded what the actuary is said.
And so what are that two is just,
what is the revenue invested in it?
These money you've said aside are those going up
to the top of the top of the top of the top of the top of the top
of the top of the top of the top of the top of the top.
Three months later, it could be a different number
because it's starting like it's changed.
And so again, that's at June 17,
the stock market had a good run-up in 18.
And then at some point it kind of fell off the cliff.
And now it's back up.
So now what the actuary is, look,
I think they generally go over a 30 year period.
When they're saying, here's how much they're fund,
is to get you funded over a 30 year period.
So it's a long, it's a long time period.
But I think it's well that the pebble is,
as long as you pay what the actuary says to pay,
if you're doing what you can.
And theoretically that ought to get you there.
Now, actually, I mean, they now have the first of all.
They're doing the best they can change.
So that's the financial report.
There's also a two-page report at the back of this.
That's the part on the state.
The thoughts about the integral controls and your compliance.
The benefit of the integral control and compliance.
But we had any issues to discuss underneath of those two topics.
That report would reference them, and there's nothing in there.
That's good news.
So the report's here, but that's not referencing any issues.
That's good.
So unless anyone else has a question or coming on the list,
that's really all I wanted to get into this.
But for four of you, I've seen it not for you all,
but I've seen it in other places with very good
as a very good job of explaining 100 and some pages
and 10 pages that you come make sense.
So this can get in a lot of control, if you're not,
and we'll be doing the performance with you and people.
Hey, Paul, let's say, they've done this audit to you, right?
OK.
The other topic now, I'll just take a second.
There's a communication letter.
It's a little two-a-three-page statement.
Well, I say it.
Two-a-three-based letter.
This is something we're required to give the government a body.
And there are seven or at both points in it that have to be in there.
Rather than you do, you can't have to talk about it or not.
They really, there's not a whole lot to talk about.
Don't do things that would point out.
that's in here.
On the attention, the actuaries, when I come out and say,
here's what we think your job that you've incurred is,
is to understand there's a bunch of estimates,
and that actually, in front of the number,
there's demographics, calling people going to live on,
and they're going to order what's your turnover,
what your pay raise is going to be,
what's the equation, what's the financial numbers,
what's the interest rate's going to do,
and the investment's going to be turned.
So obviously, the law of investments,
and every year, they've got what that does estimates,
but it is a reasonable guess, and so we're using that.
The other thing that's in here is for this year,
you have to implement a new account and standard,
and this gets a little kind of scoring on apologize,
but you all have a health benefit,
with to where, when a employee requires,
they can stay on your health insurance.
Now, they have to pay a premium to stay on it, but they can.
The premium they pay is essentially being subsidized by the city,
and so because it's subsidized, you're encouraging costs,
that is they've worked now, and so there's a liability being established for that.
And so that's about a $3,000 liability,
it's been wrong for the first time,
because of this new accounting standard.
So typically, when I hear health insurance, that they go,
when my employer is promising to pay my health insurance,
the health insurance, as long as I live until a certain day,
you won't be doing that,
but you aren't allowing them to stay on, even though they pay for it,
but it's not essentially a reduced rate.
So because of that, we're having to report another thing,
and that's not really the three million.
And that $3,000 is also, I don't know, what the proper term would be,
amortized over 30 years, it's not a one year or number.
No, that'll get us to say that every year,
and they go up and they go down, it will most likely go up,
because unlike your pension, you fund every year,
and you put money into a trust.
You set your side, that money is really protected only for the pension.
This health insurance, you're not funding as you go along.
So the liability will most likely grow over time,
but you're not funding it.
So if they're paying a number to zero,
I mean, this doesn't even have a right to get there.
But still, it's an actuarial number, isn't it?
Yes.
OK.
So it's, if we stop today, and all the retired employees
lived another 30 years, it's the estimated cost of subsidizing
their insurance for 30 years.
I'm assuming they're using 30, if that's what they're using for the entire.
It's a little different, but the good thing I actually
is going to do is just, look at your current employee base,
and say, who do I think is going to make it to that point?
How many are going to use it?
And then how long are they going to live until you're all like that?
So the 30 years is how long is actually looking out
to determine how much you should pay?
If you're underfunded, you actually doesn't say,
make it all up in year one.
They say, make it up over the 30 years.
That's the 30 years, that's the 30 years, that's it.
So that was the Southern document.
And really, that's my report.
Before I see the photo, I'd certainly like to thank
or she, Jill and Dean Ray had been wonderful
and worked with and very helpful and we enjoyed it.
And so I just thanks to them.
And we certainly appreciate the business.
And any questions for Andy?
It's always nice to get a report with no exceptions.
And a timely report.
I mean, really, it's March.
This is last year's report.
But that's really welcoming the way to get it on it
for the previous year or so.
OK, thanks, Andy.
And we don't have to accept that or anything.
It's just a presentation.
OK.
Item 8 is new business.
Any new business?
Speak up.
Item 9 is staff reports that are in the packet.
And they're available if you have questions.
Tim is mayor and council committee announcements.
City announcements anyone.
Anybody go to the ward off all school reunion?
Maybe a ward off?
I guess there's just two more ward off.
You're a ward off.
Are you the only ward off up here?
I have a ward off, but I didn't make it.
OK.
Well, never mind.
It looked like it was well-offended on Facebook.
But most of them have here greater than mine.
So city manager comments.
Just a couple of things.
I wanted to thank the street department to this ice and the snowstorm.
They were out there doing quite a bit of work.
And I wanted to just publicly thank them.
And then also wanted to thank Christine.
We had our meeting last night with landlords and re-literate sign-up.
You and Ryan were at that.
It was very happy about how positive the meeting was.
And some good ideas that were given us that were following up on, especially in regards to utilities and some communications.
And one of the suggestions made that we would agree to is trying to do this maybe on a quarterly basis.
And understanding that they're trying to put together some type of a roof of roof or not re-literate the landlords.
It might be of a work with us on some property maintenance issues and do it in a positive manner.
So it just had a room had a really good feel last night.
We weren't sure exactly what to expect.
We were very happy with feedback that we got and happy with the attitudes that were there.
And we want to keep it going and I do appreciate that you were there as well.
So it was one of the thing, Christine.
Because that was her hard work and her staff.
And they do a lot of hard work for us.
And they don't always get a lot of thanks.
So I think it's kind of the duty.
Okay, thank you, Chris, to it was a good meeting. Anything else?
Item 12 is the German. We have almost two adjourned.
And a second?
I'll a second.
Oh, call please.